Register of the Clelia Duel Mosher Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Clelia Duel Mosher papers,
1898-1937
XX249
Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1863-1940
7 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, office files, photographs, and postcards, relating to relief work of the Red Cross in France from 1917 to 1919, and to the promotion of health education for women in the United States. Includes correspondence with Lou Henry Hoover.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Biographical Note
1863 December 16 Born, Albany, New York
1893 A.B, zoology, Stanford University
1894 A.M., physiology, Stanford University
1900 M.D., Johns Hopkins University
1910 Assistant Professor, personal hygiene, and Medical Advisor of Women, Stanford University
1917-1919 Medical Investigator, Children's Bureau, and subsequently Assistant/Associate Medical Adviser, Bureau of Refugees, American Red Cross, Paris
1923 Associate Professor, Stanford University
1928 Professor, Stanford University
1929 Professor emeritus, Stanford University
1940 Died, Palo Alto, California
Scope and Content Note
The Clelia Duel Mosher papers relate to child welfare and other relief work performed by the American Red Cross in France during World War I, women war workers, and conditions in France in 1918. They also provide limited information about medical views of women's physical abilities in the 1910s and 1920s.
Mosher was Medical Investigator for the American Red Cross Children's Bureau, which provided medical care for children whose lives were disrupted by World War I. Mosher helped open a dispensary at Corbeil, establish a hospital at Limoges, and enlarge the Preventorium for Boys at Tumiac; she also took a convoy of sixty children from Paris to Evian during the bombardment of Paris. Much of her work involved inspecting and reporting on conditions at dispensaries, hospitals, schools, and other facilities, as well as some individual families in need. Her reports, in memorandum form in the American Red Cross File, describe conditions and itemize needs. While focused on institutions serving children, some reports also include general information about adults, families, communities, and public health.
The Correspondence series, in particular the letters Mosher regularly wrote to her mother Sarah Burritt Mosher, provides anecdotes about welfare work in France and general information about life in wartime France. The Speeches and Writings series includes a number of war sketches based on Mosher's experiences.
Mosher also served as an official photographer for the American Red Cross. More than 200 prints (including many duplicates) of American Red Cross personnel and activities are included in the Photographs and Postcards series. It is presumed that Mosher took many of these photographs. However, most of the prints are not identified by name of photographer or subject. The bulk of the circa 340 postcards relate to France and depict tourist sites, scenes of war damage, wartime posters, and health messages printed by the American Red Cross.
Some information about Mosher's work on women's athletics and physical education may be found in the Speeches and Writings series. Additional information is available in the Correspondence series, particularly with Lou Henry Hoover, who was Vice President of the National Amateur Athletic Federation of America in the early 1920s. Topics covered include apparel, competitive sports, menstruation, and muscular strength.
Additional papers of Clelia Duel Mosher, including the bulk relating to research work on women's physical education, are housed at the Stanford University Archives (Collection Number SC 011).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
American National Red Cross.; International relief.; Women--Health and hygiene.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.; France.; United States--Foreign relations.; Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1910-1931. (Box 1)
  Biographical sketches, certificates, commendations, correspondence, passport, receipts, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- DIARIES, 1918-1922. (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically
- CORRRESPONDENCE, 1907-1940. (Box 1-2)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1890-1925. (Box 3)
  Notes, clippings, drafts, reprints, reviews, transcript, arranged chronologically by title
- AMERICAN RED CROSS FILE, 1917-1919. (Box 4-5)
  Correspondence, index cards, issuances, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, publications, reports, transportation orders, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- PRINTED MATTER, 1915-1940. (Box 5-6)
  Booklets, bulletins, clippings, form letters, programs, reports, arranged alphabetically by name of organization or company
- EPHEMERA, 1918? (Box 6)
  Alimentation cards, baggage tags, bread tickets, leaflets, opera programs and ticket stubs, poems, ration cards, signs, unarranged
- MEMORABILIA, 1918-1919? (Box 6)
  Buttons, place card, ribbon, small steel fork, uniform insignia, unarranged
- PHOTOGRAPHS AND POSTCARDS, 1891-1925. (Box 6-7)
  Photographs arranged alphabetically by subject, followed by loose postcards and postcards arranged in an album
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1910-1931 (Box 1)
  - General, 1912-1922 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Appointment correspondence, American Red Cross, 1917 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Appointment papers, Stanford University, 1910-1929 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Biographical sketches,1919-1931 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Certificate and commendation, American Red Cross, 1919 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Passport, 1917 (Folder 1: 6)
- DIARIES, 1918-1922
  - Paris, 1918-1919 (Folder 1: 7)
  - European trip, 1922 (Folder 1: 8)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1907-1940
  - General
    - A (Folder 1: 9)
    - B (Folder 1: 10)
    - C (Folder 1: 11)
    - D (Folder 1: 12)
    - E (Folder 1: 13)
    - F (Folder 1: 14)
    - H (Folder 1: 15)
    - I (Folder 1: 16)
    - J (Folder 1: 17)
    - K (Folder 1: 18)
    - M (Folder 1: 19)
    - N (Folder 1: 20)
    - P (Folder 1: 21)
    - R (Folder 1: 22)
    - S (Folder 1: 23)
    - T (Folder 1: 24)
    - W (Folder 1: 25)
  - Unidentified
    - General (Folder 1: 26)
    - Elena, 1918-1929 (Folder 1: 27)
    - Phyllis, 1922-1925 (Folder 1: 28)
  - American Red Cross, 1919-1920 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Bassot, Mlle., 1918-1923 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Burrell, Ellen, 1917-1937 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Burrett, Emeline, 1917-1922 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Burrett, Lydia, 1922-1928 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Clayton, H., 1918-1920 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Coolidge, Mary Roberts, 1907-1937 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Farrand, Margaret, 1918-1919 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Faure, Marielouise, 1918-1922 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Haynes, Royal Storrs, Dr., 1919-1922 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Hoover, Lou Henry, 1913-1940 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Johnson, Edith E., Dr., 1917-1919 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Low, Barbara, 1918 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Lucas, June Richardson, 1918 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Mosher, Eliza, Dr., 1915-1928 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Mosher, Sarah Burritt (Mrs. Cornelius D.), 1911-1920 (Folder 2: 5-12)
  - Owen, Ethel Dale, Dr., 1918 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Palmer, Virginia Murray, Dr., 1915-1922 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Perry, Grace, 1908-1936 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Spilman, Ruth Lee, 1922 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Storey, Phyllis Moore, 1918-1923 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Ting, Me-iung, Dr., 1920 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Van Slyke, Dr., 1917 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Vickery, Martha Ellen, 1914-1918 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Walker, May E., Dr., 1918-1920 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Willcox, Mary Alice, Dr., 1915-1934 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Withington, Alfreda, Dr., 1919-1920 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Yost, Mary, 1922 (Folder 2: 24)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1890-1925 (Box 3)
  - General
    - College papers, 1890-1892 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Fragments (Folder 3: 2)
    - Notes (Folder 3: 3)
  - "All in a Day's Work," n.d. (Folder 3: 4)
    Typescript
  - "Brittany in War Time," n.d. (Folder 3: 5)
    Notes
  - "Health and Efficiency," n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
  - "Medical Examinations and Supervision of Athletics for Women," n.d. (Folder 3: 7)
  - "Personal Narratives and Letters about The California Earthquake of April 18, 1906," with Corabelle Kimball, n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
    Typescript (incomplete?)
  - "War Time Vignettes," n.d. (Folder 3: 9)
    Typescript, printed copy (incomplete)
  - "Wayside Inn," n.d. (Folder 3: 10)
  - Health and the Woman Movement, 1916. (Folder 3: 11)
    Reviews
  - "Somewhere in France, During the War," 1918 February 12. (Folder 3: 12)
    Holograph, typescript
  - "The Strength of Women," speech, International Conference of Women Physicians, New York, 1919 September 22. (Folder 3: 13-14)
    Mimeograph transcript, clippings
  - "A Spring Song," 1920 February 29. (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Madame," 1921 March 9. (Folder 3: 16)
  - "When the Class of 1918 Was Called to the Colors," 1921 March 12. (Folder 3: 17)
  - "Amalfi," 1922 September 1. (Folder 3: 18)
  - "Mothers," 1922 September 7. (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Richard Dairnaut's Wife," 1925 May 28. (Folder 3: 20)
- AMERICAN RED CROSS FILE, 1917-1919 (Box 4)
  - Card catalog of women doctors, 1918 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Diary letters of June Richardson Lucas, France, 1917-1918 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Final report, Clelia Duel Mosher, 1918-1919 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Issuances, American Red Cross, 1918-1919 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Memoranda and related materials, 1917-1919 (Folder 4: 5-9)
  - Minutes, staff meeting, Children's Bureau, 1918 (Folder 5: 2-3)
  - Proposal, Argonne Society, n.d. (Folder 5: 4)
  - Publications, Croix-Rouge Américaine, n.d. (Folder 5: 5)
  - Report, work of the Children's Bureau, William Palmer Lucas, n.d. (Folder 5: 6)
  - Reports, American Red Cross in France, 1918 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Transportation orders and passes, 1918 (Folder 5: 8)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1915-1940
  - General - Clippings
    - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1930 (Folder 5: 9)
    - War, 1915-1923 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Allied Women on War Service, 1918 (Folder 5: 11)
  - American Fund for French Wounded, n.d. (Folder 5: 12)
  - American Posture League, 1928 (Folder 5: 13)
  - American Women's Hospitals, 1918 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Angier Chemical Company, 1919 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Argonne Association, 1923 (Folder 5: 16)
  - B. Pasquale Company, n.d. (Folder 5: 17)
  - British Army and Navy Leave Club, Paris, n.d. (Folder 5: 18)
  - Butterick Publishing Company, n.d. (Folder 5: 19)
  - California Civic League, n.d. (Folder 5: 20)
  - Committee to Defend America by Aiding Allies, 1940 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Cunard Line, n.d. (Folder 6: 2)
  - L'École pour L'École, 1920 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Internationl Conference of Women Physicians, 1919 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Jean Cussac, Paris, 1918 (Folder 6: 5)
  - League to Enforce Peace, 1919 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Mead Johnson and Company, n.d. (Folder 6: 7)
  - Medical Women's Federation, 1918 (Folder 6: 8)
  - National Adult School Union, n.d. (Folder 6: 9)
  - National Amateur Athletic Federation, 1924-1926 (Folder 6: 10)
  - National Association of Manufacturers, 1939 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Paris Chamber of Commerce, 1917-1919 (Folder 6: 12)
  - La Résidence Sociale, 1921-1936 (Folder 6: 13)
  - Société des Gens de Lettres, n.d. (Folder 6: 14)
  - Stanford University, 1915 (Folder 6: 15)
  - United States. Food Administration, n.d. (Folder 6: 16)
  - United States. Office of Home Economics, n.d. (Folder 6: 17)
  - United States. Public Health Service, 1918 (Folder 6: 18)
  - United States. Treasury Department, 1917 (Folder 6: 19)
- EPHEMERA, 1918? (Folder 6: 20-23)
  Alimentation cards, baggage tags, bread tickets, leaflets, opera programs and ticket stubs, poems, ration cards, and signs
- MEMORABILIA, 1918-1919? (Folder 6: 24)
  Buttons, place card, ribbon, small steel fork, and uniform insignia
- PHOTOGRAPHS AND POSTCARDS, 1891-1925
  - Photographs
    - General
      - 16 prints depicting friends and family (Folder 6: 25)
      - 11 prints depicting North American scenes? (Folder 6: 26)
      - 2 prints depicting Stanford University (Folder 6: 27)
    - American Red Cross
      - 20 prints depicting buildings and grounds (Folder 6: 28)
      - 65 prints depicting children (Folder 6: 29-30)
      - 4 prints depicting documents (Folder 6: 31)
      - 6 prints depicting hospital treatment (Folder 6: 32)
      - 42 prints depicting landscapes and street scenes (Folder 6: 33)
      - 19 prints depicting officials (Folder 6: 34)
      - 12 prints depicting personnel in uniform (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - 16 prints depicting refugees and others (Folder 7: 2)
      - 62 prints depicting women personnel in uniform (Folder 7: 3-4)
  - Postcards
    - 55 loose postcards primarily depicting France (Folder 7: 5)
    - Souvenir album containing 385 postcards primarily depicting France (Folder 7: 6)